<?xml version="1.0" encoding="utf-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title><![CDATA[Category: Tips | Jeff Li]]></title>
  <link href="http://bluesalt.github.io/blog/categories/tips/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://bluesalt.github.io/"/>
  <updated>2017-08-12T17:17:37+08:00</updated>
  <id>http://bluesalt.github.io/</id>
  <author>
    <name><![CDATA[Jeff Li]]></name>
    
  </author>
  <generator uri="http://octopress.org/">Octopress</generator>

  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Install Protocol Buffer from Source in CentOS 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://bluesalt.github.io/blog/2016/12/08/install-protocol-buffer-from-source-in-centos-7/"/>
    <updated>2016-12-08T13:45:59+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://bluesalt.github.io/blog/2016/12/08/install-protocol-buffer-from-source-in-centos-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>Figuring out dependencies in specific distribution is really boring, not fun at all.</p>

<p>Hope this post can save you some time.</p>

<p><code>
sudo yum install autoconf automake libtool unzip gcc-c++ git -y
git clone https://github.com/google/protobuf.git
cd protobuf
./autogen.sh
./configure
make
</code></p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title type="html"><![CDATA[Build Latest Wireshark in CentOS 7]]></title>
    <link href="http://bluesalt.github.io/blog/2016/08/14/build-latest-wireshark-in-centos-7/"/>
    <updated>2016-08-14T16:27:37+08:00</updated>
    <id>http://bluesalt.github.io/blog/2016/08/14/build-latest-wireshark-in-centos-7</id>
    <content type="html"><![CDATA[<p>As we know, Wireshark has switched from GTK+ to Qt since Version 2. As a Mac and Kubuntu user, the GTK UI was really not harmony with my desktop environments. So after the version 2 was released last year, I upgraded Wireshark in both my Mac and Kubuntu boxes.</p>

<p>For some reason, I have to work on some CentOS 7 boxes in which the latest Wireshark in the yum repo is 1.10. Besides, it is difficult to find any existing Wireshark 2 rpm package in the web. After spending some time on the Wireshark document, I came to know that it is really easy to build Wireshark rpm package only if the dependencies are met.</p>

<p><code>
sudo yum install gcc gcc-c++ bison flex libpcap-devel qt-devel gtk3-devel rpm-build libtool c-ares-devel qt5-qtbase-devel qt5-qtmultimedia-devel qt5-linguist desktop-file-utils
wget https://1.eu.dl.wireshark.org/src/wireshark-2.0.5.tar.bz2
tar xf wireshark-2.0.5.tar.bz2
./configure
make rpm-package
</code>  </p>

<p>The RPM files could be found in the <code>package/rpm/RPMs/x86_64</code> directory.</p>

<p>Hope this note could save you some time.</p>

<p><strong>Updates 1</strong>
Wireshark 2.2.X has an extra dependency. If <code>configure</code> script complains about</p>

<p><code>
configure: error: I couldn't find lrelease-qt5 or lrelease; make sure it's installed and in your path
</code>
, it means <code>qt5-linguist</code> which has been mentioned in the comments by Michel, is missing. Above guide has been updated.</p>

]]></content>
  </entry>
  
</feed>
